<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Yannis Zachos</title>
    <link>https://yannisza.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://yannisza.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Yannis Zachos</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2020</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://yannisza.github.io/img/hut8.jpg</url>
      <title>Yannis Zachos</title>
      <link>https://yannisza.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic modelling of urban travel demand</title>
      <link>https://yannisza.github.io/research/stochastic-modelling-of-urban-travel-demand/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yannisza.github.io/research/stochastic-modelling-of-urban-travel-demand/</guid>
      <description>














&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/london_map_edges.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/london_map_edges.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modelling of evolution of urban travel demand is fundamental for urban planners and policy makers to assess the spatial demand for transportation capacity and decide on appropriate interventions. We follow the approach of (Ellam et al., 2018) and introduce a novel application of spatial interaction models and a mathematical evolution of their dynamics to urban travel demand. We exploit economic structure characteristics (e.g. employment) to inform travel demand between a set of origin and destination locations. The economic structural variables are described by a potential function defined in terms of utility and cost functions. We also use a system of stochastic differential equations to model temporal travel demand evolution. We calibrate our model using a Bayesian framework that formally incorporates uncertainty involved in the process due to random noise or unexplained events and propagates it into parameter inference. We apply our model to London’s 2001 commuter flow data and find that we can adequately reconstruct the flow matrix only through the use of employment data as a latent force driving travel demand. We compute a Euclidean distance-based and transportation network-based cost matrices and find that the latter is marginally better at explaining travel demand. Finally, we overcome computational challenges arising from a doubly intractable posterior by applying appropriate Markov Chain Monte Carlo schemes for various noise regimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;strong&gt;read my full report 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/files/mres_project.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;look at my codebase 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/YannisZa/stochastic-travel-demand-modelling&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian inversion of hydrological models</title>
      <link>https://yannisza.github.io/research/introduction-to-bayesian-hydrological-modelling/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yannisza.github.io/research/introduction-to-bayesian-hydrological-modelling/</guid>
      <description>














&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/3d_raw_road_view.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/3d_raw_road_view.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highways England’s objective to improve the health and safety of its customers is tightly linked to better monitoring of on-road water discharge. The increasing climate volatility can impede accurate hydrological modelling and therefore a probabilistic approach is adopted to modelling on-road rainfall-runoff. This report illustrates the potential of using a hybrid of statistical and hydrological models to better understand on-road water conditions. The study area is a major A-road in north-west of England. Three models are employed; a lumped linear reservoir (LR), a non-linear storage (NLS) and a spatially-distributed HYMOD model. These models are then used to simulate and discharge data using rainfall and potential evapotranspiration data from the Climate hydrology and ecology research support system (CHESS). The same models are treated in a Bayesian manner to make inference by assigning priors over their tuning parameters. Parameter posteriors and marginal likelihoods are computed using a Sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) sampler. Data fits and Bayes factors are examined to assess goodness of fit and identify the best model(s), which according to the data are the linear reservoir and non-linear storage models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;strong&gt;read my full report 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/files/mini_project_censored.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;look at my codebase 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/YannisZa/bayesian-hydrological-modeling&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian online changepoint detection of point processes</title>
      <link>https://yannisza.github.io/research/bayesian-online-changepoint-detection-of-point-processes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yannisza.github.io/research/bayesian-online-changepoint-detection-of-point-processes/</guid>
      <description>














&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/PG_crypto.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/PG_crypto.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This thesis details an approach known as change-point detection (CPD) that aims to detect changes in the mean, variance and covariance of a time series. The scope of CPD is limited to an on-line (real-time) Bayesian spatio-temporal setting. In this setting, the goal of CPD is to provide step-ahead predictions and partition the time series into disjoint segments every time a new datum is received using Bayesian inference. This is achieved by modelling each datum as a sample from a data-generating process which we are imitating using a probability distribution as a model. At each time step the most likely model is chosen among a universe of potential models. This leads to the development of the Bayesian on-line change-point detection and model selection (BOCDMS) algorithm which has a linear computational and storage complexity in the number of observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Model selection is narrowed by employing two conjugate point process models: the Poisson Gamma (PG) and Multinomial Dirichlet (MD) models. We study the properties of these models and assess their sensitivity and performance on four synthetic and three real-world datasets, the latter of which are related to crime in Chicago, property transactions in the UK and cryptocurrency transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;strong&gt;read my entire thesis 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/files/dissertation.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading</title>
      <link>https://yannisza.github.io/reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://yannisza.github.io/reading/</guid>
      <description>














&lt;figure&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/yannis_books.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://yannisza.github.io/img/yannis_books.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;1200&#34; &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find a list of all the books I have read so far on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.co.uk/ideas/amzn1.account.AEKGASM3Z7GYEMYYZ2OSOXB3IJWQ/1KY4HOFY0Z7V9?ref=idea_share&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;
 or on my 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/77202587-yannis&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Goodreads page.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
